Sbonelo Gumede

-- Applied Statistics and Computer Science Student

Email: gmdsbo@gmail.com Phone: +27680613359 LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/sbonelogumede

Summary

I am a final year BSc student specializing in Applied Statistics and Computer Science at the University of Cape Town. I am interested in Data Science because I enjoy using analytical thinking to systematically extract insights from data.

Experience



Department of Computer Science

Research Assistant for Professor Jan Buys

Nov 2024 - Nov 2024

• Data cleaning and data curation on large datasets to pre-train a LLM on all official South African Languages.



Department of Computer Science

Computer Science 1 Tutor

Feb 2024 - Oct 2024

 Assisted students with the course content and assignments and manual marked assignments and tests.



South African Graduate Employers Association

QuantifyYourFuture Virtual Internship | Powered by SAGEA

Jan 2024 - Feb 2024

- Exposure to real-life work experience with Absa, FirstRand, FNB and Nedbank.
- Exposure to data: framing, exploration, interpretation, modelling, and visualisation.
- Development of competency skills: critical thinking, creativity, collaboration & communication.
- Team-based projects facilitated by Absa, FirstRand, FNB and Nedbank.



Leo Marquard Hall Residence

Mentor

Oct 2022 - Oct 2023

 Assisted 10 first-year students adjust to the university and hosting mentorship fascilitated events.

Projects



Capstone Project for CSC3003S

July 2024 - Sept 2024

- YOAT Object Annotation using YOLO
 - Supervisor: Professor Patric Marias
 - Tutor: Ben Ruijsch Van Dugteren
 - Collaborators: Gumede Sbonelo, Manzi Sakhile and Mkhabela Max

• YOLO-based application to detect objects in images and videos and tracking improvement on the existing YOLO models.



Personal Website

Dec 2023 - Jan 2024

• Developed a personal website to showcase my HTML, CSS and Javascript skills.

Education



University of Cape Town

BSc specializing in Applied Statistics and Computer Science 2022 - Present



Nombika Secondary School National Senior Certificate 2019 - 2021

Achievements



Forest Hill Residence

Excellence Award

2024: Recognized for being among the top 10 achievers at Forest Hill Residence.



The UCT Plus Team

UCTPLUS Gold Award Role-Modelling Leadership

2023: Committed more than 60 hours as a mentor and submitted my Power Pitch.



Michael & Susan Dell Foundation

Dell Young Leaders

2022: Selected based on demonstrated resilience, leadership potential, and academic performance.



Ndwedwe Local Municipality

Mayoral Top Achiever

2022: Awarded for achieving 1st place in the 2021 matric results in Ndwedwe and securing 2nd place in the Ilembe District.

References

Available upon request.